{"tossups": [{"question": "For integrable systems, changing to coordinates named for this term, represented by capital I or J, ispart of straightening out flow lines. For a separable and periodic system, variables denoted by this termare a constant of motion that can be defined in terms of the area in phase space taken over one periodof the motion; those constants of motion are paired with angle coordinates. Solutions to the Euler\u00c2\u2013Lagrange equation extremize this quantity, whose critical points correspond to physical trajectories.This quantity is a functional defined as the integral, between two values of time for an input evolution,of the Lagrangian. For 10 points, name this quantity that is minimized by paths that physical systemstake, analogous to Fermat's (fair-MAH's) principle of least time.", "answer": "action [prompt on S or J]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>action</u></b> [prompt on <u>S</u> or <u>J</u>]", "acceptable": ["action"], "promptable": ["S", "J"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, the protagonist visits a pornographic bookstore run by Arthur Geiger at thebehest of a retired general. In another novel by this man, the protagonist realizes that a Mexican man isactually his friend Terry Lennox after plastic surgery. An unfinished book by this man was finished byRobert Parker and is called Poodle Springs. In yet another novel, he depicted Moose Malloy hiring theprotagonist to find his missing girlfriend. This man critiqued A. A. Milne's The Red House Mystery in hisessay \"The Simple Art of Murder\". His best known character frequently confronts femme fatales likeVivian Sternwood and Velma Valento. For 10 points, name this author whose novels Farewell, MyLovely and The Big Sleep feature his private eye Philip Marlowe.", "answer": "Raymond Chandler [or Raymond Thornton Chandler]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Raymond Chandler</u></b> [or <b><u>Raymond Thornton Chandler</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Raymond Chandler", "Raymond Thornton Chandler"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": " In retaliation for this mission, the targeted country launched a long-range balloon program known asOperation Fu-Go. United States Ambassador Joseph C. Grew witnessed this event, but, like much ofthe population, confused it with a previously planned air raid drill. Some of the men on this missionsurvived because they knew the phrase, \"Lushu hoo megwa fugi\", and others were jailed for a year inVladivostok. This operation began on the USS Hornet, and its namesake only had 467 feet of runway totake off. The planes used in this operation had their radios stripped to save weight. The namesake ofthis mission received a Medal of Honor after bailing out near Quzhou (chyoo-JOE) and meeting withChiang Kai-Shek. For 10 points, name this first attack on mainland Japan following Pearl Harbor.", "answer": " James \"Jimmy\" Doolittle Raid [or T\u014dky\u014d raid]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>James \"Jimmy\" Doolittle Raid</u></b> [or <b><u>T\u014dky\u014d raid</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["James \"Jimmy\" Doolittle Raid", "T\u014dky\u014d raid"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a scene from this film, the protagonist sits on a bench smoking as off-screen children chant thesong \"Risseldy, Rosseldy\". An aerial shot in this film shows a trail of fire caused by a salesman callouslylighting a cigar near a rivulet of gasoline. Ub Iwerks (ubb EYE-works) used the yellow screen techniquethat he co-developed to create the traveling matte shots in this film, which is scoreless despite thesound design of the director's frequent collaborator Bernard Herrmann. In this movie, the teacherAnnie Hayworth dies protecting her students. This movie ends with Mitch and the Tippi HedrenplayedMelanie leaving Bodega Bay amidst a landscape of thousands of the title animals. For 10 points,name this Alfred Hitchcock film depicting murderous avians.", "answer": "The Birds", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Birds</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Birds"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man is the usual recipient of the statement that, for those who fear to stand before the lord, therewill be two gardens. After this man is told \"Grieve not, surely God is with us\", a cave is protected by aninvisible army. His authority is challenged by the Shi'a interpretation of the Hadith of the Pond ofKhumm. This man's virtue is shown in an episode where he buys the freedom of a group of old,religious slaves. The first public speech urging conversion to the faith of Muhammad was given by thisman, and his nickname was \"As-Saddiq\", or \"The Truthful\". Because Aisha was his daughter, he wasthe father-in-law and adviser of Muhammad. For 10 points, name this man who, upon Muhammad'sdeath, was, according to Sunni Muslims, elected as the first Caliph.", "answer": "Abu Bakr", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Abu Bakr</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Abu Bakr"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Legislators in this state hope to bring back earmarks known as \"lulus\" to their districts. A corruptpolitician in this state funneled asbestos patients through Dr. Robert Taub and was named SheldonSilver. This state's governor controversially cancelled the anti-corrupted Moreland Commission,prompting a US attorney in this state named Preet Bharara to launch his own investigation into thegovernor. Its governor is a former HUD chief for Bill Clinton and the son of the man who gave therousing keynote address at the 1984 DNC. Another governor of this state appointed Kirsten Gillibrandto the Senate and was named David Paterson. For 10 points, name this state governed by AndrewCuomo.", "answer": "New York", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>New York</u></b>", "acceptable": ["New York"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Recombination-repressing chromosomal knobs were discovered in this organism. Since 1896, proteinand oil content in this organism have been researched in the Illinois long-term selection experiment. Atargeted mutagenesis technique in this organism utilizes Activator and Dissociator, or Ac/Ds, loci tobreak chromosomes. Mutations in the Tb1 gene can cause this organism to develop a branchingphenotype like that of a wild ancestor, teosinte (tay-oh-SIN-tee). This organism's color is produced by anamesake xanthophyll (ZAN-thuh-fill) carotenoid (kuh-ROT-in-oid) called zeaxanthin (zee-uh-ZAN-thin). 85percent of its genome is composed of mobile elements discovered in it, including LINEs and SINEs. For10 points, name this grass crop in which Barbara McClintock discovered transposons.", "answer": "maize [or corn; or Z. mays; or Zea mays]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>maize</u></b> [or <b><u>corn</u></b>; or <b><u>Z. mays</u></b>; or <b><u>Zea mays</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["maize", "corn", "Z. mays", "Zea mays"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Near the end of this novel, caricatures of Adolf Hitler, Mao Zedong, and Karl Marx, among others,are targeted by six fighter planes. This novel features a character who insists that any Hoosier sheencounters call her \"Mom\". This novel's narrator finds a picture of a girl named Mona in anadvertisement that also reveals the identity of the Major General of a fictional country in the Caribbean,the Republic of San Lorenzo. This novel's narrator, who planned to write a book about the day of theHiroshima bombing, discovers the religion of Bokononism. In this novel, samples of a mysteriousalternative form of water are split by Felix Hoenikker's children. For 10 points, name this novel inwhich ice-nine causes the world to freeze, written by Kurt Vonnegut.", "answer": "Cat's Cradle", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cat's Cradle</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Cat's Cradle"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A man who committed a crime against one of these places, Robert Edward Chambliss, was not convicted until 1977 because J. Edgar Hoover had suppressed evidence in his trial. Martin Luther King Jr.'s mother Alberta was killed by Marcus Wayne Chenault in one of these places. One of these places was burned down following Denmark Vesey's revolt, but was rebuilt and was where state senator Clementa C. Pinckney would later be killed. Addie Mae Collins and three other girls were killed in one of these places located on 16th Street. Dylann Roof murdered nine people in one of these places in Charleston in 2015. For 10 points, name this type of building where many Civil Rights campaigns were organized, one of which was bombed in Birmingham in 1963.", "answer": "African American churches [or African Methodist Episcopal church; or AME church]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>African American churches</u></b> [or <b><u>African Methodist Episcopal church</u></b>; or <b><u>AME church</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["African American churches", "African Methodist Episcopal church", "AME church"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of these figures stands on the back of a satyr in a collaborative painting by Jan Bruegel theElder and Rubens. In a fresco removed from the Villa Lemmi, they present gifts to Giovanna degliAlbizzi. Renaissance artists modeled their paintings of these figures on a Roman statue of them in SienaCathedral. Erwin Panofsky theorized that Raphael's Vision of a Knight formed a diptych with a paintingin which these nude figures alternately face toward and away from the viewer, holding apples. Cupidtrains an arrow on these figures in a painting in which they gather to the left of a red-clad Mercury anddance in a circle in an orange grove. For 10 points, name these three attendants of Venus who appear inBotticelli's La Primavera.", "answer": "the Three Graces [or Charites; or Gratiae]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the Three Graces</u></b> [or <b><u>Charites</u></b>; or <b><u>Gratiae</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["the Three Graces", "Charites", "Gratiae"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "World War II veterans in this country known as \"cursed soldiers\" continued to oppose its postwargovernment as late as 1963. In this country, increased food prices in June 1976 caused a series of strikesthat led to the creation of the KOR. Nine coal miners were killed here when the ZOMO riot policeopened fire on protesters outside Wujek (VOO-yeck). A major August 1980 strike in this country wassparked by the firing of an activist from the Lenin shipyard. That strike led to this country's leaderEdward Gierek (GYEH-reck) accepting the 21 demands of MKS. The 1989 Round Table Talks here led tofree elections and the end of Wojciech Jaruzelski's (VOY-chekh yah-roo-ZEL-ski's) rule. For 10 points, namethis native country of Pope John Paul II where the trade union Solidarity was led by Lech Wa\u0142\u0119sa (vahWEN-sah).", "answer": "Poland [or Polska]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Poland</u></b> [or <b><u>Polska</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Poland", "Polska"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "While in this animal form, Caer Ibormeith is identified by Aengus, who himself becomes one ofthese animals to be with her. In Book 1 of the Aeneid, Venus assures Aeneas that his fleet is safe bypointing out twelve of these creatures. Poseidon turns one of his sons into this animal after Achillesstrangles him. One of these animals that can separate water from milk is the vehicle of Brahma. Whileattempting to win the maiden of Pohjola, Lemmink\u00c3\u00a4inen fails to kill one of these animals in Tuonela.After a god took this animal form to impregnate the wife of Tyndareus, a set of half-immortal siblings,including Clytemnestra, Helen, Castor, and Pollux, were born. For 10 points, name this animal intowhich Zeus transformed to seduce Leda.", "answer": "swans", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>swans</u></b>", "acceptable": ["swans"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Mutations in the DCDC2 and DYX1C1 genes are associated with this disorder, which can also becaused by malformations in the microgyrus. This disorder has been studied by Eraldo Paulesu, whoused PET scans to measure it across cultures. It has \"surface\", \"deep\", and \"pure\" varieties, andexplanations of cross-cultural discrepancies of its effects often involve the dual-route hypothesis of thefaculty that this disorder effects. The cerebellar theory of this disorder states that it is caused byaberrations in the movement of muscles in the face and tongue, and it occurs less in languages withmore complex phonemic orthographies. For 10 points, name this learning disorder characterized byreversal of letters and impaired reading ability.", "answer": "dyslexia [prompt on reading disorder]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>dyslexia</u></b> [prompt on <u>reading disorder</u>]", "acceptable": ["dyslexia"], "promptable": ["reading disorder"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The speaker of a poem by this author imagines \"looking out to see the moon thinned to an airsharpedblade\" and muses that \"all solitude is selfish\" after receiving a dinner invitation from a mannamed Warlock-Williams. In another of this author's poems, the speaker describes seeing \"girls inparodies of fashion, heels and veils\" while he is riding a \"three-quarters-empty train\". This poet wroteabout \"the deep blue air, that shows nothing, and is nowhere, and is endless\", and another of his poemsadvises the reader to \"get out as early as you can and don't have any kids yourself\". For 10 points, namethis 20th-century British poet of \"Vers de Soci\u00c3\u00a9t\u00c3\u00a9\" (VAIR duh so-see-ay-TAY), \"The Whitsun Weddings\",\"High Windows\", and \"This Be The Verse\".", "answer": "Philip Larkin", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Philip <b><u>Larkin</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Philip Larkin"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After Paul Kisliuk observed this interaction between nitrogen and oxygen, he was determined thatthis process proceeds better around gaseous molecules, so he developed precursor state theory for thisprocess. Brunauer, Emmett, and Teller developed a theory that extends a model of this process tomultilayered molecules. The equilibrium constant of this process, times its partial pressure, divided byone plus that product, allows one to model the fractional coverage of this process, according to theLangmuir equation. Zeolites and silica gel are common surfaces for this process. For 10 points, namethis process by which molecules bind to a material's surface, but do not cross the surface and getabsorbed into the material.", "answer": "adsorption [do not accept \"absorption\"]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>adsorption</u></b> [do not accept \"absorption\"]", "acceptable": ["adsorption"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A series of papers by Alfred Dorjahn (DOOR-yawn) argued that this man's primary talent was inimprovisation. This man claimed that \"It pertains only to the gods to control fortune and to commandsuccess\" to argue that the power of assuring victory was not left up to the minister. He asked \"Shall wenot man the fleet ourselves? Shall we not take the field?\" as part of his statement that an unmannedfleet can never win a battle. This man first supported, but then later opposed, the Peace of Philocrates.He remunerated that \"Each party shall have equal audience\" in a debate with Aeschines, in which hedelivered the \"Oration on the Crown\" after the Battle of Chaeronea. For 10 points, name this Athenianstatesman who gave many speeches, such as the Olynthiacs and the Philippics. ", "answer": "Demosthenes", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Demosthenes</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Demosthenes"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This type of sum is an operation performed on two manifolds by removing a ball from eachmanifold and gluing their boundaries together. Before the removal of the dispersion point one-halfcomma one-half, the Knaster\u00c2\u2013Kuratowski fan possesses this property. The topologist's sine curve is atextbook example of a space with this property that does not possess this property locally. Acomponent of a topological space is a maximal subset with this property. Spaces with trivialfundamental groups are called \"simply, [this property]\". A topological space has this property if itcontains no proper, nontrivial subsets that are both open and closed. For 10 points, name this propertythat a graph has if there is a path between every two vertices.", "answer": "connected [or word forms, such as connectedness]", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>connected</u></b> [or <b><u>word forms, such as connectedness</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["connected", "word forms, such as connectedness"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A choral piece about this event is scored for a soprano soloist plus full orchestra, tenor and basssoloists plus chamber orchestra, and boys' choir plus organ. In the wake of this event, a D major pianoconcerto was written in one movement, but with a slow\u00c2\u2013fast\u00c2\u2013slow structure, and it opens with acontrabassoon solo. Six movements dedicated to participants in this event make up Le tombeau deCouperin. In the aftermath of this conflict, specialized pieces were written for Paul Wittgenstein, such asMaurice Ravel's Piano Concerto for the Left Hand. A sacred piece about this conflict sets poems such as\"Strange Meeting\" and \"Anthem for Doomed Youth\", both by Wilfred Owen. For 10 points, name thisconflict that inspired Benjamin Britten's War Requiem.", "answer": "World War I [or the Great War; prompt on partial answers]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>World War I</u></b> [or the <b><u>Great War</u></b>; prompt on <u>partial answers</u>]", "acceptable": ["World War I", "Great War"], "promptable": ["partial answers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": " In one of his few political texts, this philosopher joined with Liam Murphy to claim that basing taxpolicy on the notion that \"we earn our income and the government takes some of it away from us\" is a\"robust and compelling fantasy\". In a later book, he argued that an \"immanent order of nature\" shouldbecome an accepted part of scientific theories, arguing that what he labeled \"neo-Darwinianmaterialism\" is \"almost certainly false\". This co-author of The Myth of Ownership advanced a theory of\"agent-neutral\" motivations for action in \"The Possibility of Altruism\", and wrote another paperclaiming that, even if a human acquired the ability to fly and echolocate, that would not duplicate theexperience of being biologically prepared for those behaviors from birth. For 10 points, name this NYUprofessor, who argued against the possibility of understanding animal consciousness in \"What Is ItLike to Be a Bat?\".", "answer": "Thomas Nagel", "category": "Philosophy", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Thomas Nagel</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Thomas Nagel"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": " In a play written in this language, two young people appear in the frames of two portraits thatformerly showed the title character and his beloved Matilde. In another play in this language, someonewho calls himself the \"Maniac\" enters a police station, where an arrested man has just fallen from awindow. A character from a play in this language comes to believes he is a king after falling off hishorse. This language used to write Accidental Death of an Anarchist and a non-Shakespearean Henry IVwas also used in a play in which the Little Girl drowns in a fountain and the Father meets the StepDaughterat Madame Pace's brothel. For 10 points, name this language used to write Six Characters inSearch of an Author by Luigi Pirandello.", "answer": "Italian [or italiano; or lingua italiana]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Italian</u></b> [or <b><u>italiano</u></b>; or <b><u>lingua italiana</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Italian", "italiano", "lingua italiana"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character created by this author harbors a grudge against a woman who protested when he stolea piece of toast off of her plate, and accuses a friend of fabricating a story about a man who was sent toa hospital after being mugged. Another play by this author includes a monologue whose speaker saysthat we shouldn't trust God to deal with one-in-a-million occurrences. He wrote a play in which Donand Teach plan to rob a customer who had gotten a good deal on a rare coin from a junk shop. Inanother play by this writer, Ricky Roma successfully plays the role of the salesman with Lingk, andShelley Levine tries to buy a set of good real estate leads from his boss. For 10 points, name thisplaywright of American Buffalo and Glengarry Glen Ross.", "answer": "David Mamet", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "David <b><u>Mamet</u></b>", "acceptable": ["David Mamet"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}